[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is Goran petrovich a staff
software engineer at Google Goran
focuses on on software quality
improvement through the development and
evaluation of new software tools and
processes welcome to the show thanks
Greg it's good to be here today during
our episode we're going to be talking
about goran's effort to introduce
mutation testing at Google we're going
to start by exploring what mutation
testing is and the ways in which
Google's software Engineers tend to use
it now Goran I know you published a
paper called state of mutation testing
at Google and if you won't mind I'm
going to read you a sentence from the
paper and then invite you to comment on
it does that sound cool sounds great
okay so the paper was called the state
of mutation testing at Google and the
sentence was mutation testing assesses
test Suite efficacy by inserting small
faults into programs and measuring the
ability of the test Suite to detect them
so at a high level can you tell us what
is mutation testing and how does it work
sure so everyone is familiar with the
standard criteria like line coverage and
it's been in standard in the industry
for many years and mutation testing is
just a step further in this to ensure
that the code is not only covered with
tests but actually properly tested in
terms of assertions you could imagine
that you can have a function that you
call from a test and don't assert
anything it can have 100% coverage but
it will never catch any real bugs and
mutation testing comes to help in terms
of actually validating that these tests
do something useful the big picture is
that why do we even write tests maybe 20
years ago or 10 years ago people were
complaining that they had to do it and
they they said we don't need that now
it's more or less a standard but the
real question is why do you do it and
the reason is we don't want bug to be
introduced into the code and then pushed
to our users so the best way to do that
is to actually have tests that can catch
these bugs not only that cover certain
lines of code so mutation testing is a
system where you can just change the
code change the implementation by
mimicking a bug in a way let's say
replace a plus b with a minus B and then
run all the tests if no tests fail
there's something wrong there so you
might have coverage but this is not a
good test and mutation testing is a way
of generating many of these different
code versions with slight changes they
are called mutants and then running all
the tests on all of them and calculating
the score mutation testing score which
tells you how many many of these mutants
your tests were able to detect and then
that's another number along with
coverage that can help you understand
the quality of your tests even better so
what you're explaining is interesting
and yet it may sound somewhat
counterintuitive because normally we
associate testing with the process of
getting bugs out of our code but you've
explained that mutation testing is
putting bugs into our code can you
unpack that a little bit further why
would we want to put a bug into our code
sure I do that every day programming is
an art of adding bugs to your code and
then removing them and probably you
never remove all of them there's some
remaining so you could say that
99.99% of code that I write is full of
bugs and eventually it will have so few
bugs that they won't be so important so
I can actually release my code and
that's a good reason to try to insert
bugs into the code because it's
inevitable that we will do it as human
beings we are not evolved to write
complicated code we are evolved to run
around in the the woods so this is very
hard to hold concentration and the bugs
will definitely happen so mutation
testing is just a natural way of
simulating that you just say imagine if
you make a bug here imagine if you if
you inserted a bug here what would
happen and people sometimes ask like but
I I didn't so my code is correct why
should I care but software engineering
is uh integrated programming over time
so usually if you just write a code for
like a one-off script or a competition
that that's okay but most of the code
that the compan write will live for
years and years decades even and you as
an author are just the first author
there will be countless changes
happening to the code some from your
team with the people who are familiar
with the code but some from completely
different people who want to add a
feature or want to do a refactoring and
even I don't understand most of the
things that I'm writing about let alone
if I'm editing someone else's code so
the chance of me introducing a bug is is
huge and that's why we want to protect
against that so if I'm understanding you
correctly when I put these small faults
or mutants in the program and my test
Suite detects them then I know that if I
later put that into my program the test
Suite would still detect it is that the
right idea it is and of course a student
might ask I'm not going to write in a
function of sum a minus b instead of a
plus b but the idea is that these small
changes these mutants they might not
look like real bugs but then they are
correlated with real bugs so this is the
core assumption if that doesn't hold
then mutation testing doesn't make any
sense but it happens to hold so that's
the reason why inserting these small
non- buug looking changes actually if
you prevent them you can also prevent
bugs by tests you made a really good
point about the correlation between
these mutants and real bugs and we're
going to talk about your experience at
Google later in the episode specifically
in that area before we move on I wanted
to pick up on something you said a
moment ago you were talking about like a
plus b and then you mentioned a minus B
if I remember correctly is that what you
mean when you talk about the concept of
a mutant yes that's one example of it
there have been many many different
mutant operators developed over the
years and the mutant operator is just a
fensive way of saying how do I change
your code to insert a bug into it so
when you encounter any binary operator
Like A Plus or a minus you you can
replace it with a division or or a
subsumption of any other operator that
would fit in that code so that's an
example of a mutant yes or you can just
say if a equals B you can just say if a
not equals B you can negate the operator
so you given an example of not equals
and equals and plus and minus can you
give one or two more concrete examples
of mutants sure the most boring mutant
is deleting statements let's say delete
a line but because of the structure of
the code they are the most prevalent
because you cannot replace a plus with a
minus in every line of code it might not
even have a plus you cannot negate a
condition because not every line
contains a condition but almost every
line can be deleted so while it is
boring it is the most common mutant just
delete a statement delete a line delete
a block let's say you have an if
statement and you just delete the whole
else block that's one of the mutants
that you could do others are just
changing numbers from 0o to one changing
strings from whatever the string
literally is to an empty string you can
always change the do an absolute of and
then negate the number this is one of
the mutants that in Google we don't do
because it turned out to be the least
useful of all mutant classes that's an
interesting consequence of of doing this
research but yeah whatever type of
change you can imagine there have been
mutation operators proposed and
implemented for that those are very
simple that I've been describing but
they are more complicated mutants you
could just cast a pointer into a base
class
or do something strange with
objectoriented mutations or for each
language for example lisp you can do
multiple other different things and so
on one of the things that I heard you
say a moment ago is that mutation
testing is this strong test adequacy
Criterion and if I remember correctly I
think you said it was stronger than code
coverage criteria like statement
coverage or Branch coverage can you tell
us a little bit more what is a test
adequacy Criterion and then why is
mutation testing quote quote stronger
than these code coverage criteria sure
Greg so it's very simple you can define
a criteria let's say coverage of lines
and just count the lines that are
covered overall lines and you get a
percentage and this is your Criterion
and test Suite you can say it's adequate
according to this Criterion if it covers
100% of lines and so on for mutants it's
a bit different because you generate all
the mutants that you can in the code and
then run all the test Suites and all of
them and you calculate the percentage of
of the killed mutants and this is your
your your mutation score or mutation
adequacy score and if it's 100% which
I've never seen it means that all the
mutants in the code have been killed the
issue with the with this is that it's
while coverage is very well defined each
line is either covered or not Branch
coverage as well each branch taken or
not mutation testing is defined in a
sense that either a mutant is killed or
not but it is not defined in the domain
of mutants I have yet to see two
different mutations testing tools that
can generate exactly the same mutants on
the same piece of code there are
different optimizations there are
different underlying Technologies used
that will yield different results and
that's why when you cannot compare these
numbers across across tools or
programming languages or even your own
invocations of the same tool on the same
code I noticed you mentioned the idea of
a mutant being killed can you explain
what that concept is all about sure so
when you have mutated code let's say
that the function sum that I talked
about before that is just returning a
plus b suddenly it's changed into a
minus B that constitutes a mutant
hopefully there will be some kind of a
unit test that will fail when you do
this if you assert that 2 plus 2 is four
suddenly these mutants will return as
zero and this is not good hopefully
there's a test that test is and if the
test fails any test covering this line
fails we say that this mutant is killed
by this unit test and the tests that are
not killed are called living orive live
mutants and they are more interesting
than the killed ones because they are
the ones where you can actually add
stuff to your test to make them better
all right that makes a lot of sense I
have two more quick questions before we
go to the next part of our show I
noticed that you've been mentioning a
process for mutation testing what I'd
like you to explore a little bit further
is whether this process is manual or
automated for example does the software
engineer actually insert these mutants
themselves or is there tool support for
this process
sure there is widespread tool support
and it's all completely automated as a
developer you don't have to do anything
just wait until the system reports the
living mutants in your code and then you
can react on them this sounds like
really an exciting thing and I can
imagine why software engineers at Google
would be interested in using it however
with that said I remember that in one of
the articles that you wrote you said in
2016 that mutation testing was only used
used as a part of 93 code reviews at
Google and then it grew to roughly 2,500
users in
2017 and by 2021 there were tens of
thousands of Engineers at Google who
were using mutation testing so now that
we understand the basics of what
mutation testing is my question is as
follows why was it initially hard to
convince Engineers to use mutation
testing because they're smart people by
Design mutation testing generates a huge
amount of mutants and then shoves them
down your throat when I started
implementing this what I did is I read a
bunch of research papers I was really
excited I started coding and in a few
weeks I had something that worked
originally for C++ and then I started
generating these mutants the basic
system was just reporting those mutants
that were alive in the command line and
you could just look at them and you can
save them into a file and go one by one
and my first run I remember it took a
few hours to run I ran it on on a small
code base of my team I was back then in
Google shopping when it finished I
looked at the file and could barely open
it in Vim it was huge there were
thousands tens of thousands of mutants
and after three pages and two coffees I
was so tired that I just closed the file
and forgot about it for a few weeks
because there was huge amount of mutants
and most of them were not things that I
would actually be adding tests for I
wouldn't want to have that tested
against we call these unproductive
mutants but that was the first stage and
then of course because I this was my 20%
project something that I would do on
Fridays only and I forgot about it for a
few weeks and then later when I
continued I realized this doesn't work
like I cannot even myself who is excited
about mutation testing I cannot convince
myself to look at this for more than 10
minutes so I just decided at that point
that we have to prune this somehow and
the first step was just to figure out
what these unproductive mutants were
let's say you have a log line and you
delete the log line of course the test
doesn't fail because it doesn't catch
that and you would be surprised but
there are thousands of categories of of
of mutants like this that are not
interesting some of them might look good
at the beginning but then you quickly
realize this is not something that the
developers would want to write tests for
so slowly but surely I started adding
this encoding these heuristics as a
filter so I would not consider these
lines of code to mutate at all the log
line is the simplest one you can do it
in 10 minutes but as I said there are
thousands so it took it a long time but
once I was happy with the number of
mutants in the output I started getting
my team to use it that's the 97 full
request in Google that you see it's all
my friends who who did it because I
asked them to they probably didn't like
the tool because it still it wasn't the
quality wasn't High the number of useful
mutants the percentage was like 12% I
think at that point not very useful but
with their feedback they would be
labeling my set for me they would just
say this mutant is useful this isn't and
then over time could encode more and
more of these heuristics that's how we
got to a much better number I think now
it's around 90% useful 10% not useful
mutants that's why it took a long time
and that was the first big Improvement
huge amounts of these heuristics and
then the second was I realized that
while when you have these automatically
generated tests probably using some kind
of a genetic algorithm that is trying to
fit some criteria let's say killing
mutants the test that they generate will
probably kill just one mutant in in that
line because that's what they do they
evolve to do it but humans are
sufficiently evolved to not write such
tests so you wouldn't test half of a
line or a third of the line or even like
some kind of a ve subcondition we try to
write good tests that are useful and
they usually kill all the mutants in
that line so I realized if I wanted to
run this for more than just my team I
calculated once back of the envelope it
would take seven billion years with all
the computing power currently available
in for All Humans to do one iteration of
our two billion lines of code to
calculate the mutation score so
obviously the universe didn't like what
I was doing but I wasn't discouraged by
that I just decided I'm not going to
generate any of the mutants in a line
more than one and then I'm going to pick
that one at random and that was the
second that second hurdle once we got
past that we could start opening
mutation testing to other teams because
it wasn't as annoying and it wasn't as
useless thank you those were some
incredible insights and I can absolutely
see why you had to limit the number of
mutants that you would actually present
to a software engineer I noticed a
moment ago you talked about mutants that
are not useful like for example mutating
a logging statement can you give us an
example of a mutant that you would
consider useful and then explain why
it's useful sure let's say that in this
simple summation example A plus b most
mutants are useful if you replace that
with return zero then that's a useful
mutant it means that you're not really
testing anything another example would
be a function that determines whether
user is of age or not something for your
website so you would have something like
return user age greater equal 18
depending on the country and uh this
mutant that replaces this with true or
false is useful but I mean coverage can
tell you that you probably did not just
return false in that in that function B
user is always under age you probably
have something there so those are less
useful but still can indicate coverage
but coverage is much cheaper to
calculate and then you should be using
that instead but if you change that to
greater than instead of greater equal
than 18 then it might catch a corner
case if you're not implementing that the
the user of 18 is still not of age so
that's that's a very useful mutant there
and if it survives it will just detect a
bug immediately in your code hopefully
it will not because you implemented it
perfectly the first time but these are
just small examples there are billions
of lines of code and any kind of this
Edge case where you do greater than
equal or greater than is very useful
especially with iterators and the
inclusive exclusive intervals and so on
these are really tricky to get right and
mutation testing helps there a lot
thanks for sharing those concrete
examples those made a lot of sense one
of the things that I've heard is that
sometimes a specific type of mutant
might motivate a software engineer to
write something called a change detector
test can you tell us what a change
detector test is and whether whether or
not that's a good or bad type of test to
write and how that connects to mutation
testing sure change detector test is a
test that will fail most of the time
whenever you change anything in the code
so you're not really testing the
implementation you're testing some kind
of implementation detail or the
specifics an example might be that
you're catching an exception and
asserting the exact contents of that
exception and that's usually a bad
strategy because you might be changing
that messaging you should be asserting
on the type of the exception and in
these kinds of Errors it should return
this type of exception but you shouldn't
care about the contents or you could
assert of the subset of the contents
that you're more or less certain are not
going to change you don't want to depend
on like a the debugging output of some
kind of a function that is represented
in the exception because that might
change an underlying object might change
its own representation and then you're
going to be have to fix your test
ideally well- written test Suite you
could completely reimplement your
feature your code
everything based on everything new and
you just rerun the test and they all
pass that's that that means that you
have mastered the art of testing but I'm
not there yet are there examples of
certain types of mutants that tend to
motivate an engineer to make this type
of negative change detector test
definitely so we have tried over the
years to suppress them using these heris
sixs so we wouldn't report these and we
always say in our findings please don't
add a test unless you actually think
it's useful and then we have the code
reviewers that probably would not let
you at the change detector test because
they would say this is not a useful Test
please don't do that and so there we
have a lot of guard rails for this but
the types of mutants that that usually
produce this are things that for example
will change the exception message let's
say or add a one or a minus one
somewhere where it's but it's not being
used arithmetically but it's being used
for let's say metrics or logging or
sleep or whatever and then people might
be
to kill that mutant but that's not a
productive mutant they shouldn't they
shouldn't do that but I think with all
the guardrails I think we're doing well
there okay that example makes a lot of
sense in a moment we're going to start
talking about the tools that you're
building at Google in order to actually
perform mutation testing however before
we get there I'm wondering could you
tell us a highlevel story about how
mutation testing has improved the
quality of some software product at
Google sure so those numbers are always
hard to get but many people will send us
emails Thanking us that the team that we
have found prevented bugs and we have
gathered a lot of examples like this
over time it's always something like
there is a small bug in the code and
then people with the mutant they notice
this but if they just add a test to fix
that that's that's one thing that's a
small Improvement maybe you never
introduced this kind of a bug so it's
it's very hard to try to guess the
future value of this new test case
but often people would just say this is
an equivalent mutant meaning that mutant
it does the same thing as the one as the
original code so you cannot kill it
because it's equivalent to the original
code but it makes them see something in
their design and they just say oh yeah
we need to completely change this and
then they they they refactor the code
and they are much happier with it and
sometimes it can be something that is
not testable at all and because of this
mutant while trying to kill the mutant
they have to change the code make it
testable make it better and then there
are secondary improvements I would say
even Primary in this case where this
refactoring comes into play okay that's
interesting so it sounds like sometimes
mutation testing might help you to
improve your test Suite but in other
occasions it may actually help you to
refactor your program and improve its
design is that the right way to think
about it yes and we have a paper that
looks into this and we have found that
this is the case there's a lot of mutant
that are resolved by changing the code
not adding tests usually both okay
that's incredible we'll make sure to
link to that paper in the show notes
before we move on two quick additional
comments first of all can you tell us
anything about the prevalence of
mutation testing at Google today I
haven't looked in a while but I would
guess more than 50% of Engineers are
exposed to mutants during their normal
development cycle okay thank you that's
really helpful and then finally before
we move on I know that sometimes people
people talk about mutation testing and
then they also use an Affiliated phrase
which is mutation analysis what are the
similarities and differences between
mutation testing and mutation analysis I
was also first confused by this because
when I when I came to mutation testing I
came to it directly as an engineer not
as a as a researcher of any kind so for
me what I wanted is to take this idea
and make it useful to the developers and
that's why there's this differentiation
mutation analysis is is just this
adequacy thing that we talked about
before just getting the ratio of killed
mutants over all mutants and then you
have this number while mutation testing
is an attempt to capitalize on that on
that technique and get improvements in
the code base mostly in tests from these
developers and in the end it's very hard
to try to convince developers to look at
100,000 mutants in their project and
then most of them are not actionable
they will just not do it it's a reality
that we have to face and during code
review it was the best location for
actual mutation testing where you where
you have a already an attention of a
developer and you you can present some
hints how they can improve code while
all the other tools are doing that as
well like coverage or testing Frameworks
or linters and so on other analyzers and
this is the best place to try to smuggle
some kind of extra information for them
so they might act on it and then
Implement new tests okay thanks for that
response I think it is helpful to know
that these mutation testing results are
presented to a developer at Google
during the code review process if our
listeners want to learn a little bit
more about how software engineering at
Google works they're welcome to check
out software engineering radio episode
609 where we talked with hyam Wright all
about software engineering practices and
processes at Google Now what I'd like to
do is to turn our attention to the
implementation of the tools that you've
created
the overall system seems to be called
mutagenesis if I'm pronouncing that
correctly and as you mentioned a moment
ago it's a part of the analysis and code
review process can you tell us a little
bit about some of the specific
components or features of this
mutagenesis tool that I mentioned a
moment ago sure so the best way to get
developers to do something and to act on
on some results is to introduce the
least amount of friction in their
workflow so you should integrate either
in the IDE shifting left if you can or
in the code review tool or in the
release tool or any other
wellestablished process that they're
used to already so for mutation testing
it made sense that it's introduced into
the code review because it depends on
test results and coverage and this is
where all of that happens anyway so this
was just a natural extension and the way
mutation testing works is that it waits
until coverage is calculated for a given
pull request when it's sent for review
View and then it calculates a map from
each covered line to a set of tests that
actually test this line This is critical
because if you didn't have coverage
information you would just have to run
all tests for each mutant and that would
be very very expensive so we have to
just wait until coverage is complete and
then filter all the tests by those that
cover the line making it much cheaper so
the next step is then this analyzer will
take this information and it will
generate mutants using this mutagenesis
this process in all of the eligible line
lines of code so it will take the
covered lines of code and it will filter
from the heuristics that we talked about
before the mutants that we don't
consider productive and then the
remaining lines will be mutated only a
single mutation as I said and then the
set of mutants will be actually created
and test run executed against them and
then finally you will have a report if
there are any living mutants in your
code you will get a finding in the code
review on that line saying something
like if your code is changed like this
let's say a plus b to a minus B then no
tests pass please consider adding tests
uh to cover this if I'm understanding
correctly there's a mut Genesis server
for the various programming languages
that you supported Google can you give
us some examples of programming
languages for which you're able to
perform this kind of automated mutation
testing sure what we support is C++
python Java
go typescript JavaScript cotlin Dart
common lisp SQL and most recently rust
wow that's really cool so if there's a
mutagenesis server for each language do
you implement that server in the
language that it is targeting can you
explore that process a little bit
further and explain how you actually
build this mutation testing tool support
sure that's the most interesting part
for me I always like compiler Theory and
playing around with the abstract syntax
trees so that's the most fun for sure it
depends on the language so for C++ we
use clang because it can give us type
information it is slower than the simple
pares you would use but C++ is so
complicated that I think clang is the
only way to do it properly a light
weiter system might just parse it using
some kind of a parser generator and that
would be fine but you wouldn't be able
to do all the kinds of suppressions that
we do detecting pointer types for
example and comparisons with zero or
null pointer they cannot be done without
a proper compiler front end for Java use
an open source Java parser in Java for
go we just use its own and python their
own internal ASD libraries that I have
well for python we don't have too much
type information but python doesn't
really have type information anyway so
it's I think it's good enough Lis is
interesting lisp is its own parser and
compiler so everything is done in lisp
rust is in Rust using the macro
framework which is quite nice it's
strong enough that you don't need to use
the actual compiler you can just use its
own internal macro as it works quite
well JavaScript is interesting because
that's done in Java because our compiler
for JavaScript is in Java historically
so that's done that closure so it's done
in Java for typescript it's done in
typescript itself and it's quite nice
and no problems there cotlin and dart as
well are done in cotlin and dart so it's
mostly in their own the only ones are
like the nodejs and for typescript I
think that's and SQL is done in C++ it
would be even I'm not crazy enough to
try to implement an ASD parser in SQL
itself so it could be maybe done but
that's done in C++ okay that makes a lot
of sense I remember a moment ago you
referred to something called the a or
the abstract syntax tree and that made
me think and in fact I'm wondering when
you're doing this parsing of the C++
codee or the dart code or the python
code do you parse that to some type of
common intermediate representation that
all mutagenesis servers understand or do
they use the python as or the C++ a that
comes from that specific parser can you
explore that a little bit further
definitely that's a very good question I
don't have a good answer what the best
strategy is but I can tell you what we
do and we have a different as and
different framework for each of these
languages there are some some things
like the treer and the whatever it's
called parser generator libraries that
can parse everything to a degree they
don't give you type information for all
languages some are supported I think
like go and Java are usually supported
there is a compiler frontend for them
even in these generic as Frameworks but
in the beginning I just hacked it and I
liked cing lvm I liked playing with it
it was was nasty it was very hard to
make any progress but that's what makes
it fun I suppose I think now for most of
the mutators it takes me a week to
implement them first two days to figure
out how to do recursive visits of the
tree and then it takes me two or three
days to implement all the mutators like
for changing plus to minus for negating
things for deleting lines and so on but
yeah I tried once to migrate everything
to this common infrastructure but I gave
up quickly because I couldn't get this
pointer type information for C++ which
is used in few heris that are important
although I would like to to finish that
project one day and then compare because
I don't really know what the impact
would be of not having it but I know I
give up there okay you mentioned a
moment ago something called a treesitter
parser and although we won't investigate
that during our discussion today we'll
put a link in the show notes to the
treesitter parser and what it is and how
it works many people have probably used
that because it's integrated into their
text editor
and it helps them with syntax
highlighting but to be clear you're not
using treesitter in your current
implementation is that the right way to
understand it yes in each language we
use its own native support for parsing
except for SQL and JavaScript where we
use Java and C++ libraries that
implement the parser so the idea of a
mutator is that roughly speaking it
takes as input an abstract syntax tree
and it produces as output a mutated
abstract syntax tree that has this
synthetic bug inside of it at a high
level is that the right way to think
about the tool I think so yeah practical
implementations are usually simpler you
don't have to mutate the actual tree
because that's sometimes hard what you
do is you just find let's say you find
an A plus b somewhere or if a plus b
greater than five you first check that
it is in a line that's been covered then
you check that it's not in an
unproductive line let's say a log line
and if that works out then you can just
remember I am in this line from this
bite offset to that bite offset from
this character to this character I have
to change this width and you can just
throw a die and say I'm going to change
it to a minus B and then you just
remember that the plus is at this offset
and you just replace it with a minus and
you just have to remember the edit when
generating mutants that's enough to take
the original code and just do a simple
substring operation on it that's much
easier than actually mutating the whole
tree okay that makes a lot of sense now
I know you mentioned a moment code that
you're focusing on like a specific part
of the change in the code so I'm
guessing that means that when someone
commits code you don't do mutation
outside of the region that they're
committing is that correct it is and the
original design was always like that
because this was very natural for us
like everything is done there anyway so
I never really thought about doing
anything more it was only when I started
talking to researchers and going to
conferences reading papers that I
realized that I was the outlier I
thought that this was how it's done but
yeah for us you can imagine this
yourself if someone sends you a pool
request to review why would you care
about a file that is in seven
directories away that you don't know
about that you are not an owner of you
have never seen before and there is a
mutant there like it is not let's say
useful information in terms of the
probability of you actually reacting on
it so we want to the developer attention
is the most precious resource we have we
don't want to
annoy them in a sense because mutation
testing very few Tools in Google are
mandated most of the things people can
use it if they want to and they can opt
out if they want to if they don't like
your tool in the two days they will just
disable it for them and then you lost
the user so we have to be very careful
in how we present the information we
have to filter a lot we have to even
lower the number of mutants per let's
say per 100 files lines we can have at
most let's say 10 or five we have to we
be played with that number historically
because you don't want to overwhelm the
developer as well because you have to
remember this is just a small tiny
analyzer tool in the whole sea of
hundreds of analyzers that are running
all the time and the developer just
wants to get done with their work they
want to submit their pull request and
unless you're most often on the spot you
will lose a user you mentioned that the
engineer is a precious resource at
Google and certainly that makes sense
your comment though also made me think
of the fact that mutation testing is
associated with something that's very
expensive and I remember in one of your
papers you mentioned something like
there are 500 million tests that are
being executed at Google every day and
that it's gatekeeping something like
60,000 code changes and yet somehow
mutation testing is still scalable even
though you're running 500 million tests
every day so Goran that's astonishing
what is it that allowed you to make
mutation test scalable at Google even
though it's something that's associated
with being very very computationally
expensive that's a very good question as
I said before the universe doesn't like
us running all of these tests if you
want to get the mutation score for a
repository it's not possible but if you
filter out most of the mutants we call
it aggressive suppression her istics if
you mutate only lines of code that have
changed in the code review in the pull
request that have been covered within it
and then filter aggressively and then
generate only one mutant per line and
not more and then even have additional
limits in the number of mutants per file
or per line changed then you have
reduced number of mutants by 90
something per that you have to evaluate
and this makes it feasible and Google
has a very cool infrastructure for
building and testing and evaluating
stuff so there's a lot of caching
involved when you compile a piece of
code and you just change one line you're
going to get 99% or higher of compiled
cache object cache so mutants are always
compiled in such a way that you compile
once and then all the mutants each is
just a small change on top of the
previously compiled blob so it's it's
quite efficient in doing that so if a
software engineer is making a change to
the Google code base if you could give
an example how long does it take to run
mutation testing on that code change it
usually takes a few minutes but that
depends on a few things one is of course
the size of the change we don't for
example run mutation testing on very
large changes especially the lscs the
large scale cleanups that are automated
we don't run them on any automated or
autogenerated pull requests only on
human generated pull requests and
usually takes a few minutes but as you
remember you have to wait until tests
are done and then coverage is done which
is whatever it takes for that before we
only start running mutation testing
after those two things are done but most
of the the time I think it's done before
of course the request is submitted okay
thanks that's really helpful if
listeners want to learn more about some
of the things that we mentioned they
could check out episode 59 which is
about static analysis or check out
episode 324 which connects to code
coverage analysis Goran before we go on
to the ways in which you've evaluated
mutation testing tools at Google is
there anything else that you'd like to
highlight about the implementation of
the tooling that you've created well I I
think the only interesting difference
from the open- source implementations of
mutation testing and what we have is
that we actually generate the mutants
based on the ASDS there are some open
source tools that do that as well but
it's usually prevalent to change the
bite code in Java or the intermediate
representation of llvm in C++ and I
think the main reason for that is that
for us it's very important to be able to
show the developer exactly how the m
would go they have to actually look at
it and you have to show them and that's
very hard to do if it's based on the
bite code I think that those tools are
great and I use them but it's just
sometimes impractical to show to render
the actual diff okay and I'm glad you
brought that up so you're saying you
actually changed the source code
directly one of the mutation testing
techniques that other people have
developed to achieve scale is by
embedding all of the mutants into
something called a metam mutant do you
use metam mutants in the tooling that
you've built at Google or did did you
adopt a different approach so I think
the reason why we don't have the mega
mutants is that I was lazy and this was
easier to do I think they are a great
idea but you have to compile everything
only once but as I said before the
compilation overhead is not too big when
you have very good object caching so
that wasn't such a big deal for us
because to evaluate one mutant it takes
let's say 100,000 compilation actions
but then for the every subsequent one it
only takes a single one so that makes it
cheaper and I also wanted to do the
metam mutant implementation but I didn't
just have the time yet hopefully in the
future okay that makes a lot of sense
we've covered a lot of cool
implementation details but what I want
to do now is to dive into a discussion
about how you actually evaluate these
tools and whether or not you can sense
that they're giving clear value to the
engineers at Google so one of the
studies that you ran said that you had
almost 15 million mutants
and you had collected data about
mutation testing at Google over a
duration of an entire 6-year period so
first of all I got to say wow that is
super exciting and then second of all
I'm just wondering do developers
actually write more test cases when they
are shown these 15 million mutants
that's a very good question so we also
asked that question of course our
intuition was they of course did because
we did but working with research you
always have to measure things and you
have to show that they're true which I
think is a very very very good strategy
because we've also found things that
were not true here luckily it turns out
that if you present mutants to
developers they will add more tests and
how we measured this was when you send a
pool request for review there's a
certain amount of code in it and a
certain amount of testing in it right
and you have sent it for review when you
submit it this will again contain the
submitted pull request will contain some
amount of code and some amount of
testing in it if the approv was given
immediately and there's no feedback and
there are no comments and there's no
mutants it would probably be the same it
would just be as is you sent it for
review no comments let's submit fine but
when you have mutation testing comments
saying please add a test to kill this
mutant please add a test to kill that
mutant we find that the submitted code
has more tests than they do in the
control which is everything else that
doesn't have the mutants in them and
furthermore this in itself is not too
exciting you could have more tests that
don't really contribute to catching bugs
to having high quality because as I said
before you could just call a function
from a test and cover it completely 100%
but have zero assertions in your test
meaning that you have 100% coverage you
have added more tests we have detected
you adding more tests but it doesn't
really serve in catching any bugs
preventing outages so we also looked at
the correlations of these bugs like the
mutants that are alive when you send a
pool request
and the mutants that are alive when you
actually submit the code and we have
detected these consistently going down
for the C's pull request within Google
it's a perforce changelist name we have
noticed that these pull requests that
had mutants now have less live mutants
so the test actually killed them which
is great news because if they just added
coverage and not kill detect mutants
they would not be as useful okay so it
sounds like what you're saying is that
the developers are not only writing more
test cases but they're writing better
test cases because they can detect more
of these synthetically seeded mutants is
that the right way to understand it
exactly okay now we mentioned this
earlier in our conversation and I want
to revisit it now you talked previously
about something that's called the
coupling effect Goran can you explain
what the coupling effect is and how you
studied it in your experiments at Google
sure so as I said before the mutants
that we insert don't really look like
real bugs that humans do no one is going
to just return false from the whole
function that has to do some logic but
the coupling hypothesis says that these
mutants are similar to bugs in a way
that they actually the test cases that
catch these mutants will also likely
catch the real bugs and the coupling
measurement you could say is that if you
had 100 bugs you could see see how many
times there would also be a live mutant
that would correspond to it and then of
course if you write a test to kill this
mutant it also should detect it bug and
this is the coupling ratio that's really
interesting so have you done any
experimental studies that show if you
detect this type of mutant it helps to
avoid this type of bug going into
production at Google do you have a story
that you could tell about that sure we
have done this analysis of taking
hundreds or even thousands of actual
bugs and this is not easy because mining
bug repositories is very very hard if
you don't look at each bug the
distribution is going to be completely
wrong because no project keeps a
consistent let's say bug hygiene so it's
very hard so we had to actually look
into each of these bugs and make sure
that they are real bugs that happened in
code and we found an Associated fix to
this bug so what we did there is just
analyzed whether when this bug was
introduced
there would have been a mutant had
mutation testing been enabled for this
project and if so would the fix usually
adds a test as well would the added test
to the fix also kill this mutant and in
I think 69% of cases it was the case
that the bug and the mutant were coupled
so that means that if these test had
been written had mutation testing been
enabled these bugs would have been
prevented so that sounds like it's an
easy way to make a clear win argument
for the introduction of mutation testing
sure but it was very expensive to
calculate okay that makes a lot of sense
I'm wondering if we could take a quick
step back there are many different ways
that we could improve the overall
quality of our software and you've
mentioned test coverage analysis and
we're talking about mutation testing now
I'm wondering can you give us your
intuition how did you know that it was
the right time to introduce mutation
testing at Google given the analysis
pipeline that you already already had in
place well that's a funny story I had no
idea I joined the team in Google
shopping and as it used to be the case
everyone had a 20% project and my
manager said oh we started dismutation
testing last hackathon maybe you can
inherit it and I'm like oh I have no
idea what this is I've never heard of
this but I will inherit it because I
don't really have a choice right so I
started reading those papers and
eventually rewrote all of their code
because it was a hackathon project one
week of like just try to get a proof of
concept working and then it became my
project over time so it was their idea
and I don't know where it came from
because it was before I joined the team
but I just pushed and pushed for years
to get it done and I mean most things
you can get done the question is how
much you have to change the original
idea for it to be feasible and I mean I
call this it's a capacity-driven
development like if you cannot run all
the mutants then choose a subset that
makes sense if you cannot evaluate at
all lines well drop some and I mean you
have to eventually come to a workable
thing that still brings value you don't
have to implement whatever was Invision
50 years ago on paper right so I think
for many project like this good enough
is good enough those are several very
interesting examples so again focusing
on a specific line or maybe even
randomly selecting a specific mutant are
there any other experimental results
that you have discovered that have
ultimately helped you to enhance the
mutation testing tools at Google there
was one idea we had but we finally
didn't do it because we didn't think it
was ethical but it was just like a
random analyzer that would pick a random
line in the code and said oh maybe you
should look at this line again and think
about it in the end we didn't do it but
it was a fun experiment but in mutation
testing yeah many improvements that
we've done over the years for the
framework some of them are just these
eristics I added one today I still get
after I think it's been 9 years people
still will say this is not ause mutant
and then I will go and look and I will
try to figure out how I can suppress
those kinds of mutants you cannot
imagine how many logging Frameworks we
have how many wrappers of logging
Frameworks we have and all the other
things like caching mechanisms because
if you look at it the caching mechanism
if you remove it it doesn't change the
functionality it just makes your thing
go slower if it's uncached so any Mutant
around caching will be an equivalent
mutant and learning about this from our
users and just implementing the support
for that is the way we have improved the
tool the most I think this sounds like
an awesome experience and you've been
mentioning these various heris from a
back of the envelope perspective are we
talking about 20 heuristics or hundreds
of heuristics what kinds of heuristics
are built in and roughly speaking how
many are there so considering there are
11 languages there are thousands of
heuristics but many of them fall into
the same group let's say don't mutate
calls to these kinds of functions so
logging
functions things like let's say
collection capacity let's say you
construct a vector you can give it an
initial capacity but you can reduce it
by one and nothing's going to happen
because the vector is going to grow
there is no change the same goes with
the Java Collections if you just
increase the capacity of a collection it
will just grow or Shrink as it needs to
it won't change the behavior so all of
these are you could say there are 50
different containers with five different
initialization methods I would call them
a single heuristic but there are like 50
instances of each of those so in in that
terms I would say there are like five or
six groups of her istics and then
thousands of instances of them and we
have a tsse extension that has an
appendix that is like 10 pages long
listing examples from these okay we'll
make sure to reference that in the show
notes so other people can pick it up I
have to say this has been a fascinating
and thought-provoking conversation what
I'd like to do now is to turn our
attention to some of the broader lessons
that you've learned from introducing
mutation testing to the engineers at
Google the first thing that I've heard
you mention more than once during our
discussion today is that sometimes
you're taking ideas from research papers
on mutation testing and then you're
trying to introduce them into practice
and studies at Google what have you
learned from that process can you tell
us a little bit more definitely that's
been a very interesting Journey so what
I've learned is that as I said before
developer attention not only at Google
not only developer just human attention
is the only resource in the universe
that's worth thinking about so wasting
it is always a bad idea I think so just
thinking about how you can improve the
product and the development process is
the best way to start so people are
sometimes if you have an idea you you
read the paper you just want to present
it as it is and build it in and any
deviation from it gives you resistance
that's I think a bad approach you just
think how we can help our product or our
teams how can they be more efficient how
can they have less bux in production and
then work backwards from there and then
I think that way things fall into place
you've invested significant effort and
time in building these tools and I'm
assuming you're using the tools on a
regular basis as well can you tell us
what have you learned and how are you a
better software engineer after you've
built and started to use these mutation
testing tools they are annoying as hell
I know when I send a pull request for
review I know I'm going to get a mutant
and I know exactly where because because
I've implemented it and I already start
writing an extra test for it because
it's it's so annoying and then sure it's
there and it's in that line the most
annoying thing is even when I fixed that
there's another that I didn't see coming
so I think people learn to anticipate
them and immediately when they write
code they see oh this test only covers
this left Branch I need to add something
for the other Branch as well so they I
think I have certainly started writing
more more tests to cover more cases and
we have measured this as well that over
time there's this thing that we called
exposure I think over time as you have
been using mutation testing for a longer
time you tend to write more tests
proactively even in the beginning when
you send your initial pull request you
tend to have less live mutants over time
and more added Code test and I've
definitely noticed this in myself H
that's a fascinating result as we draw
our conversation to a conclusion I want
to pick up on several things that you've
said and ask you to give advice to two
different groups of individuals so first
of all do you have advice for
researchers who are building mutation
testing tools or studying their
effectiveness and then additionally
there are many listeners who want to
know how they can get started with
mutation testing so can you give some
advice to both of those groups sure so I
have to admit my bias of a large company
Viewpoint the way to start using
mutation testing is very simple just
Google mutation testing you will find
for your language a tool that is good
and you can try and try and run it my
main advice would be initially integrate
it immediately into the workflow
whatever it is GitHub workflows or what
whatever you have Jenkins Hudson no
matter what because asking people to do
an extra thing a day is probably not a
good idea and no matter if it's at work
or at home and of course suppress
mutants as much as you can find a tool
where you can just ignore most of them
because otherwise no one is going to
look at thousands of them that would be
my advice okay that will be helpful and
will in fact link to some of the GitHub
repos for various tools like pit for the
Java programming language or mut mut for
python or striker for JavaScript I think
those are all helpful ways for people to
get started are there any other things
that you would like to share as an
advice to a software engineer who wants
to learn mutation testing and maybe try
it out for the first time definitely I
think also as you asked before for
researchers what we all would like is to
have I would say user Centric view of
mutation testing or analysis just think
in terms of something that someone in
some company can pick up a paper read it
and then sit down and Implement that and
then get some benefit from it I think I
find those papers the most interesting
and for people starting out I think
patience and also keeping in mind that
the end goal is not to to kill mutants
it's not to write tests it's to make
better products wow that's a great point
to conclude on in our conversation today
we've talked about mutation testing and
you've hinted at the key idea which is
that ultimately mutation testing helps
us to achieve higher quality software I
know that there may be something we've
overlooked are there any additional
topics that we should briefly discuss
before drawing our discussion to a
conclusion the only one that comes to
mind it would take us 10 years to I
think conclude so we can skip it but and
that is the question of quality we don't
know what quality is we cannot measure
it okay now for those of you who are
interested in investigating the idea of
quality you might want to read the book
Zen In The Art of Motorcycle Maintenance
but we'll leave that discussion for a
later time Goran thank you so much for
being on the show it was a great
pleasure to chat with you today is there
any final call to action that you would
like to share with our listeners no I
think that's it thank you Greg thank you
Goran for those of you who are listening
and interested in learning more I hope
you'll check the show notes so that you
can explore mutation testing and learn
how to use goran's insights and tools
inside of your own software development
Adventure thanks Goran talk with you
again soon
ciao thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on on each episode on the
website or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook
Twitter or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licens under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening